<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>
      famubu: Home
    </title>
    <link>
      https://ju-sh.github.io
    </link>
    <description>
      Updates from ju-sh.github.io
    </description>
    <generator>
      Script using https://codeberg.org/ju-sh/mrkup
    </generator>
    <language>
      en-us
    </language>
    <atom:link href="https://ju-sh.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>
        Panel discussion - RSD 7 @ IITPKD
      </title>
      <link>
        https://ju-sh.github.io/blog/panel-rsd7-iitpkd.html
      </link>
      <description>
        
&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Notes from the panel discussion held as part of RSD 7 at IITPKD
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;content-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research scholars day of IIT Palakkad for the year 2025 (RSD 7) was held between February 21st and 22nd. As part of this event, a panel discussion was held which went over matters related to research life. The panel consisted of professors from IITPKD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is an outline of the thoughts from this session. (Occasionally augmented with my own comments. So this may not be exactly what was discussed.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn not just to answer a question but &lt;strong&gt;to ask the right question&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at recent papers in your field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify the common source of truth that these paper seems to derive from&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start research from that point and figure how to arrive at that source of truth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ie, See what is the &lt;strong&gt;common direction of the papers&lt;/strong&gt; being published and try to arrive at the source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remark: Hitchhiker&#x27;s guide to galaxy quote
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the answer to life, the universe, everything? 42.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then what is the meaning of the question ??!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ie, before finding the answer, one should have a clear idea of the question.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number of publications vs quality of research
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quality should matter more than quantity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unfortunately, Quality is not quanitifiable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Difficult for a group of people to rank papers based on quality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Number is the only metric by which can be agreed upon by everyone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For this reason, number of publications is often used to decide who gets promotion, funding, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quality is not quanitifiable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suggestion: &lt;strong&gt;Focus on quality, but don&#x27;t neglect quantity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About advisors potentially pushing student to publish review papers
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since review papers are much more likely to accumulate citations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review papers is not original research, but is literature review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suggestion:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Literature review is a critical skill in research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But literature review must lead to new ideas being explored&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One shouldn&#x27;t stick to writing review papers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like in the case quantity vs quality,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Literature review
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should know the state of art before starting the actual work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helps avoid duplication of effort&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are likely to gain insights&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding a research topic
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seek something that you are passionate about&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Know more about it. Read literature. Talk to people working in that domain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See how you can advance the state of the art.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See what contribution can you make to make the work of future researchers easier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Something that others can build on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ie, &lt;strong&gt;find something that you are passionate about and see how to make that better&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incremental research vs breakthroughs
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most research is incremental in nature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A PhD work usually extends the boundaries of knowledge a little bit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although breakthrough ideas are nice, that is not for everyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In maths, 10 mediocre theorems may be easier to prove than one big theorem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Method used by a panelist to identify a worthwhile proof:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write the proof, keep it away for a few weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By now you probably can&#x27;t recall the details of the proof.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Come back and read what you wrote earlier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are amazed by the proof, it is great.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Otherwise, it is mediocre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Importance of research collaboration
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to meet people: Attend conferences, summer schools, webinars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establish connections while attending events
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send a mail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have a concrete idea to work on, keep at it don&#x27;t let lie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collobrations should be with people whose expertise you can complement&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This also allows both parties to better appreciate each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both parties bring something new to the table, thereby achieving something that neither would&#x27;ve been able to achieve alone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Casual conversations sometimes lead to full blown collaborations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Story shared by a panelist: 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Panelist published a paper in an interdisciplinary domain with a collaborator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The collaborator and the panelist were members of the mess committe of their institute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While running an errand related to the mess (buying samosas), they had a chat about their areas of research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This eventually led to a colloboration resulting in a paper.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A professor in the audience remarked that this is another reason why students should consider joining the mess committee. :D&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suggestions:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk about your research to anyone who would listen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask about others&#x27; research and listen to anyone who has the time to talk about their work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowing which journal to submit to: 
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It could help to know the expertise of editors before submitting to journal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even for good quality submissions, if the reviewer is not familiar with the topic, they could judge it poorly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Role of AI/ML:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AI isn&#x27;t everything, nor is it nothing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can make positive contributions
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eg: Chatgpt is capable of helping people make beamer slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These days applications of AIML is being helpful in almost every domains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To know the benefit of applying concepts or output from another field, there should be interdisciplinary communication
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eg: Mechanical dept student should talk with CSE/Data science to learn how AIML can help them automate some of their work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disadvantage: Big applications like chatgpt is difficult for normal people to run on their own.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have to depend on vendors who could charge users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether it will take away jobs?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probably.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once computers began to get popular, many jobs vanished&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But computers did make life better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideally, people should be capable of adapting to changing environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concern: What if people start depending on AI too much that they &#x27;forget&#x27; how to do the things that they come to depend on AI for?
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remark by panelist: Similar to a scenario in an Isaac Asimov novel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As in, there are inteliigent machines, but no human knows to build one anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not an invalid point, I guess.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use of computers and calculators has made mental arithmetic less necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But people can now possibly use the time spent on mastering mental arithmetic skills to do other work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The novel: &lt;em&gt;Prelude to Foundation&lt;/em&gt; - 1st prequel in the &lt;em&gt;Foundation&lt;/em&gt; series&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example of handling hostile paper reviews
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reviews are usually helpful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a review&#x27;s tone is hostile, disregard the tone and use the feedback itself if it makes sense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the reviewer is being unnecessarily hostile, contact the journal&#x27;s editor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eg: A paper review mentioned that the submitter is arrogant because of the delay in incorporating suggested changes. Even though there was no direct communication between submitter and the reviewer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish your PhD as soon as possible
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During a PhD, you will be making much less money that you would if you were in the industry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every extra year you take to complete PhD is loss of great amount of money and immense amount of wasted value in terms of time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You do your best work when you are young&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use your youth to do good work and gain experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you get old, you are less likely to be energetic, but you can use your experience to help collaborators and still get good work done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great insights are derived from past experiences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ie, time is limited. Use it effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting stuff:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IEEE seems to have banned the world &#x27;novel&#x27; from the titles of papers that it publishes
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Probably due to too many papers using it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Couldn&#x27;t find the source)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joke?: Review of a 4 page write-up spanned 5 pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The students who organized the event&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moderator: Dr. Albert Sunny&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Panelists:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Dinesh Jagadeeshan (Dept. of Chemistry)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Jaikrishnan Janardhanan (Dept. of Mathematics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Kesavan D. (Dept. of Mechanical Engineering)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Sabarimalai Manikandan (Dept. of Electrical Engineering)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just for fun, here&#x27;s the part from Hitchiker&#x27;s guide to galaxy (book version) mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;em&gt;The hitchhiker&#x27;s guide to the galaxy&lt;/em&gt; by Douglas Adams:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Seventy-five thousand generations ago, our ancestors set this program in motion,&quot; the second man said, &quot;and in all that time we will be the first to hear the computer speak.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;An awesome prospect, Phouchg,&quot; agreed the first man, and Arthur suddenly realized that he was watching a recording with subtitles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;We are the ones who will hear,&quot; said Phouchg, &quot;the answer to the great question of Life …!&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;The Universe …!&quot; said Loonquawl.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;And Everything …!&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Shhh,&quot; said Loonquawl with a slight gesture, &quot;I think Deep Thought is preparing to speak!&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a moment&#x27;s expectant pause whilst panels slowly came to life on the front of the console. Lights flashed on and off experimentally and settled down into a businesslike pattern. A soft low hum came from the communication channel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Good morning,&quot; said Deep Thought at last.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Er … Good morning, O Deep Thought,&quot; said Loonquawl nervously, &quot;do you have … er, that is …&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;An answer for you?&quot; interrupted Deep Thought majestically. &quot;Yes. I have.&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
The two men shivered with expectancy. Their waiting had not been in vain.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;There really is one?&quot; breathed Phouchg.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;There really is one,&quot; confirmed Deep Thought.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;To Everything? To the great Question of Life, the Universe and Everything?&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Yes.&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
Both of the men had been trained for this moment, their lives had been a preparation for it, they had been selected at birth as those who would witness the answer, but even so they found themselves gasping and squirming like excited children.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;And you&#x27;re ready to give it to us?&quot; urged Loonquawl. &quot;I am.&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Now?&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Now,&quot; said Deep Thought.&lt;br/&gt;
They both licked their dry lips.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Though I don&#x27;t think,&quot; added Deep Thought, &quot;that you&#x27;re going to like it.&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Doesn&#x27;t matter!&quot; said Phouchg. &quot;We must know it! Now!&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Now?&quot; inquired Deep Thought.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Yes! Now …&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Alright,&quot; said the computer and settled into silence again. The two men fidgeted. The tension was unbearable.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;You&#x27;re really not going to like it,&quot; observed Deep Thought.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Tell us!&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Alright,&quot; said Deep Thought. &quot;The Answer to the Great Question …&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Yes …!&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Of Life, the Universe and Everything …&quot; said Deep Thought.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Yes …!&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Is …&quot; said Deep Thought, and paused.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Yes …!&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Is …&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Yes …!!!…?&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Forty-two,&quot; said Deep Thought, with infinite majesty and calm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a long time before anyone spoke.&lt;br/&gt;
Out of the corner of his eye Phouchg could see the sea of tense expectant faces down in the square outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;We&#x27;re going to get lynched aren&#x27;t we?&quot; he whispered.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;It was a tough assignment,&quot; said Deep Thought mildly.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Forty-two!&quot; yelled Loonquawl. &quot;Is that all you&#x27;ve got to show for seven and a half million years&#x27; work?&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;I checked it very thoroughly,&quot; said the computer, &quot;and that quite definitely is the answer. I think the problem, to be quite honest with you, is that you&#x27;ve never actually known what the question is.&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;But it was the Great Question! The Ultimate Question of Life, the Universe and Everything!&quot; howled Loonquawl.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Yes,&quot; said Deep Thought with the air of one who suffers fools gladly, &quot;but what actually is it?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A slow stupefied silence crept over the men as they stared at the computer and then at each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Well, you know, it&#x27;s just Everything … Everything …&quot; offered Phouchg weakly.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Exactly!&quot; said Deep Thought. &quot;So once you do know what the question actually is, you&#x27;ll know what the answer means.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>
        Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT
      </pubDate>
      <guid>
        https://ju-sh.github.io/blog/panel-rsd7-iitpkd.html
      </guid>
      <category>
        outline
      </category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>